Guide to the H. G. Merriam Papers 1890-1980
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
H. G. Merriam Papers
1890-1980
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 487
Merriam, H. G. (Harold Guy), 1883-1980
17.25 linear feet and 2 oversize boxes
H. G. Merriam was a University of Montana professor who played a crucial role in the development of Montana and Northwest literature. This collection contains personal and professional correspondence as well as working copies from Merriam's writing and editing endeavors. Significant subject categories include Merriam's service during World War I; long involvement with the Rhodes Scholarship program; teaching and administrative activities at the University of Montana--Missoula; founding, editing, and leadership contributions to the Frontier and Midland journal of regional literature; and activities to help create and guide the Montana Institute of the Arts.
Biographical Note
Harold Guy Merriam was born September 6, 1883, at Westminster, Massachusetts. He was graduated from Denver (Colorado) High School in June 1902, and entered the University of Wyoming where he majored in science and the classics. He received his BA from Wyoming in 1905. In 1904 he was chosen to be a member of the first group of Rhodes Scholars. He attended Lincoln College, Oxford University, where he was enrolled in the honors school in English language and literature. He was awarded a BA from Oxford in 1907 and an MA in 1912.
Merriam taught at Whitman College in Walla Walla, Washington, from 1908 to 1910. In the fall of 1910, he enrolled at Harvard University as an Austin Fellow. Merriam left Harvard, where he studied drama, after the fall term to teach a Beloit College in Wisconsin, where he remained until 1913. He then taught at Reed College in Portland, Oregon, until 1919. During World War I, Merriam took a leave of absence from his teaching career and went with the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) to France, where he taught English to French officers. After the Armistice he was transferred to London, where he assisted American officers and enlisted men in entering British universities.
The University of Montana hired him in 1919 to teach English and to chair the English department. Merriam introduced creative writing into the curriculum. To encourage his students to write, he began editing their works and publishing them in a new magazine, the Frontier. This later merged with the Midland, published in Iowa City, IA, to form Frontier and Midland. This well-respected regional literary magazine encouraged students and writers not only from Montana, but from throughout the Pacific Northwest. The publication featured the early efforts of regional writers A.B. Guthrie, Dorothy M. Johnson, Helen Addison Howard, Grace Stone Coates, and others. Publication of the journal continued until 1939.
Merriam began a series of writer's conferences in Montana in the summer of 1930. These short conferences offered creative writers the opportunity to work with such nationally known writers as Struthers Burt, Mary Austin, Frank Ernest Hill, and others. The conferences continued through the summer of 1934, were suspended until 1948 and continued through the summer of 1960. Following the formation of the Montana Academy of Sciences in 1940, Merriam formulated the idea for the Montana Institute of the Arts, which was founded in 1948. He served as its first president and in 1957 became the editor of the Montana Institute of the Arts Quarterly, a position he filled until 1964.
From 1907 to 1919, the University of Montana had no Rhodes Scholars. Merriam became very active in the program; with his encouragement, sixteen University of Montana students went to Oxford between 1919 and 1970. He was an enthusiastic supporter of the program and served many years on its regional and local committees. In 1933, in addition to his duties as chairman of the English department, Merriam was appointed chairman of the Division of Humanities, a new concept in University administration. He continued carrying the two assignments until his retirement in 1954. In December 1935, Merriam was appointed state supervisor of the Federal Writers' Project. His efforts culminated in the publication of Montana, A State Guide Book in 1939. He also took leave from the University of Montana in 1939 to teach at the University of Oregon in Eugene, and earned his PhD in English from Columbia University.
Merriam was instrumental in the recognition of the importance and accomplishments of American and Northwest writers. Prior to his work and that of others, literary studies in the United States were largely confined to British authors; an individual with a college degree in English would usually have studied no American authors. In recognition of his accomplishments, the University of Wyoming awarded him an LLD in 1962, citing his record as "Rhodes Scholar, professor of literature, founder and editor of magazines for new writers in the Northwest, anthropologist of regional writing, pioneer in the discovery of the cultural potentialities of his region." In 1963, an honorary LLD followed from the University of Montana Missoula. In 1978, he was honored at the 75th dinner celebration of the Rhodes Scholars in New York.
He married Doris W. Foote in 1915. They had two children, Alan and Alison. Doris Merriam died in 1970, and he married Frances Dummer Logan in 1974. H. G. Merriam died in Missoula, Montana, in March 1980.
This collection contains materials reflecting the diverse interests and activities of H. G. Merriam. Collection materials are predominantly personal and professional correspondence as well as working copies from Merriam's writing and editing endeavors. Significant subject categories include Merriam's service during World War I; long involvement with the Rhodes Scholars program; teaching and administrative activities at the university in Missoula; founding, editing, and leadership contributions to the Frontier and Midland journal; and activities to help create and guide the Montana Institute of the Arts.
Merriam was one of the seminal figures in fostering the literary traditions of Montana as well as the Northern Rocky Mountain region. Materials in this collection provide significant insights into the personal and professional relationships among literary and performance artists, academic leaders, politicians, and art patrons throughout the 20th Century, a period of tremendous cultural change regarding the mass distribution of popular culture materials and the western states' transition from cultural depository into a nationally recognized resource for arts and literature.
Materials in the Rhodes Scholars series lend first-hand insights into the infancy of the program and long-term efforts to retain a collegial approach in selecting new participants. The University of Montana series reveals the inner-workings of an institution transformed by the demographic, political, and cultural changes that occurred in the United States during the 20th Century. A particularly significant portion of this series documents activities surrounding Merriam's dismissal from the university in 1939, one of many academic freedom controversies that occurred around this time. The Frontier and Midland is recognized as the first regularly published literary anthology for Montana and the Northern Rocky Mountain region. Materials in the series record Merriam's commitment to establishing and promoting standards for folklore collection, editing, source acknowledgement, and publication. The series includes numerous sequences of correspondence between Merriam and many of the most influential figures in Montana and Western literature. The Montana Institute of the Arts series documents the founding and development of a significant grassroots arts and humanities program in the state. The Writings and Writings of Others series provide insights into Merriam's multi-faceted literary projects as well as his influence on contemporaries. The Photograph series includes a wealth of materials documenting the activities, gatherings, and publications of the Montana Institute of the Arts and other aspects of Merriam's career.
The collection is divided into twelve series:
Series I: Personal, 0.25 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1890-1980
Series II: General Correspondence, 1.25 linear feet, 1905-1980
Series III: World War I Service, 4 folders, 1918-1919
Series IV: Rhodes Scholars, 7 folders, 1904-1979
Series V: University of Montana, 1.5 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1919-1979
Series VI: Frontier and Midland, 5.0 linear feet, 1921-1973
Series VII: Montana Institute of the Arts, 2.25 linear feet, 1941-1980
Series VIII: Writings, 5.5 linear feet, 1902-1980
Series IX: Writings of Others, 13 folders, 1926-1970
Series X: Awards and Honors, 0.25 linear feet, 1920-1975
Series XI: Scrapbooks and Photo Albums, one oversize box, circa 1900-1939
Series XII: Photographs, 2.25 linear feet, 1914-1975
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Most of Merriam's collection remained in his possession until his death in 1980, though he seems to have given some initial part to the archives in 1979 and before. Other materials were acquired by non-family members and were donated to the archives after Merriam's death. Details of how these materials were acquired and housed were not recorded upon donation to the archives.
H. G. Merriam gave some portions of his papers in 1979 and before. The bulk of the collection was a gift of Alison Merriam Payne as trustee of his estate in 1980. The Margaret Ronan manuscript, edited by H. G. Merriam, was donated by Arthur Deschamps through the Friends of the Mansfield Library in 1980. Richard Ormsbee also donated a single letter in 1980.
Seven books donated by the Merriam estate were separated from this collection during 2003 reprocessing. Considering the age and unusual context of these publications, all seven were incorporated into the Mansfield Library Special Collections materials. The separated books are: Specimens of Pre-Shakspearean Drama, Volumes I and II (John M. Manly, Ginn & Company, 1897), Beowulf (A.J. Wyatt, editor, Cambridge University Press, 1901), The Works of Edmund Spenser (R. Morris, editor, MacMillen & Company Limited, 1904), The Literature of the Rocky Mountain West, 1803-1903 (Jay L. Davidson and Prudence Bostwick, editors, Caxton Printers Ltd., 1939_Review Copy), The Northern Plains in a World of Change (Carl F. Kraenzel, Watson Thomson, and Glenn H. Craig, Gregory-Cartwright Ltd., 1942), Medieval English Prose (Roger S. Loomis and Rudolph Willard, editors, Appleton-Century-Crofts Inc., 1948), The American University: How It Runs, Where It Is Going (Jacques Barzun, Harper & Row Publishers, 1968).
The American Heritage Center at the University of Wyoming holds 0.25 cubic feet of correspondence that Merriam sent home to his family from France, 1918-1919, and portions of Merriam's diaries during his residence at Oxford University.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
College professors--Montana--Missoula
American fiction--Montana; American fiction--Northwest, Pacific; Arts--Montana; American literature--Montana; Creative writing--Periodicals; Creative writing (Higher education)--Montana--Missoula; Literature publishing--Montana; Rhodes scholarships; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Young Men's Christian associations
Montana Institute of the Arts; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.). Dept. of English; University of Montana--Missoula--Faculty; University of Wyoming--Alumni and alumnae.
Frontier and midland
Photographs; Scrapbooks
Montana; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Arts and Humanities; Colleges and Universities; Literature
- Personal, 1890-1980; Series I; 0.25 linear feet and partial oversize box
  This series includes an assortment of material reflecting H.G. Merriam's early experiences, family activities, and personal interests. Biographical materials include a first grade report card from 1890, an early letter of recommendation written by Merriam's high school principal, draft resumes, testimonials, and a eulogy. Also included is an undated caricature of H. G. Merriam that was likely produced for a yearbook section. Clippings from various periods of Merriam's life lend insight into his professional activities and personal interests as well as his attention to family and friends. A small selection of financial and legal documents detail matters ranging from Merriam's personal book holdings to his charitable gifts, from family budgets to his first wife's final will and testament. This series also contains an undated proposal to construct a public mall at the intersection of Higgins and Broadway avenues in Missoula, Montana, including an architectural drawing drafted by Merriam.
  - Biographical, 1890-1980 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - "The Contretemps," University of Wyoming Yearbook, 1904 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Clippings, Merriam Lectures, 1908-1936 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Caricature of Merriam, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Merriam Family Budget, 1931 and 1938 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Certificate, Appointment as Madison County Deputy Sheriff, 1950 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Clippings, Alan P. Merriam, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Gifts to the University of Wyoming, 1962-1980 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Gifts to Libraries, Various Universities, 1962-1971 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Gifts to Museums and Historical Institutions, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Personal Book Inventories, 1964 and undated (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Clippings, Students and Colleagues, 1972-1976 and undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Ethel Merriam Will, 1974 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Contacts at Other Universities, undated (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Architectural Drawing, Proposal to City of Missoula, undated (Box-folder 40OS/1)
  - Historical and Architectural Interests, 1926-1971 and undated (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Property Survey Certificate, 1977 (Box-folder 40OS/2)
- General Correspondence, 1905-1980; Series II; 1.25 linear feet
  This series contains an array of correspondence, both incoming and out-going. During 2003 reprocessing items of correspondence directly regarding subjects in other series were relocated to those series. Items include incoming correspondence written in French, advice on job searches, job offers, acceptance to graduate study programs, and organization of various writers' conferences. Prominent correspondents include federal elected officials, state political leaders, university presidents, nationally and regionally renowned authors, scientists, and significant figures in literary criticism. Among these correspondents are U.S. Senators Joseph Dixon, Mike Mansfield, James Murray, Thomas Walsh, and Burton Wheeler of Montana as well as university presidents C. Valentine Boyer of the University of Oregon, Dexter Keezer of Reed College, Ernest Holland of Washington State University, and James Morrill from the University of Minnesota. Correspondents also include literary figures Struthers Burt, Grace Stone Coates, Bernard DeVoto, Frank Hill, Joseph Kinsey Howard, Dorothy Johnson, Frank Bird Linderman, John Lomax, Norman MacLean, Archibald MacLeish, Ogden Nash, Theodore Spencer, Mildred Walker, and Robert Penn Warren as well as scientists Albert Einstein and Edwin Hubble.
  General correspondence after 1954 is predominantly editorial exchanges between Merriam and budding authors. Most of these authors were Montana citizens seeking first-time publication of articles, short stories, or historical novels; however, these materials also include a few authors from other western states. Merriam's extensive correspondence with Lucia Mirrielees provides significant insight into their friendship and how Merriam helped to nurture her career as a writer and teacher at the University of Iowa's Bread Loaf School, Stanford University, and the University of Montana. Materials regarding Montana, The Magazine of Western History include several extended exchanges that provide interesting insights into the management and mission of a fledgling regional historical literature magazine. Some of these topics include a political imbroglio surrounding Senator Richard Neuberger's service on the Regional Board of Editors, organizational debates regarding the role of various advisory boards in editorial decision-making, and controversies generated by Michael Kennedy during his tenure as Editor.
  Materials are arranged chronologically, with separate folders for individuals with especially extensive correspondence.
  - General Correspondence, 1905-1912 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - General Correspondence, 1913-1917 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - General Correspondence, 1918-1922 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - General Correspondence, 1925-1930 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - General Correspondence, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - General Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - General Correspondence, 1938 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - General Correspondence, 1939 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - General Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - General Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - General Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - General Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - General Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - General Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - General Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - General Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - General Correspondence, 1961 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - General Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - General Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - General Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - General Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Family Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Browne, Maurice, 1924-1949 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Carnegie Foundation for Advancement of Teaching, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Gray, Gordon, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Linderman, Frank B., 1919-1938 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Mirrielees, Lucia, 1925-1931 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Mirrielees, Lucia and Edith, 1932-1957 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Montana, The Magazine of Western History, 1955-1978 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Northern Montana College, 1962-1963 and undated (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Readings for the Blind, Montana State Library, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Reed College, 1913-1971 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Riasanovsky, Antonia, 1940-1954 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Robinson, Lennox, 1924-1962 and undated (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Streit, Clarence, Nobel Nomination Correspondence and Support Materials, 1980 (Box-folder 4/7)
- World War I Service, 1918-1919; Series III; 4 folders
  The materials in this series document Merriam's service during WWI as an English instructor for French officers. The series includes several documents detailing Merriam's involvement with the Canadian wing of the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), the organization that facilitated Merriam's wartime service.
  - Booklet for teachers of French Soldiers, 1918 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Clippings and memorabilia, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Military documents, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5/4)
- Rhodes Scholars, 1904-1979; Series IV; 7 folders
  This series includes records from Merriam's participation in the first group of Rhodes Scholars as well as his lifelong commitment to the program as a solicitor, trustee, and selection committee member.
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1904-1913 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Personal Notes, ca. 1904-1913 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Oxford Exams, 1905-1907 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Clippings, 1907-1978 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Committee Documents, 1935-1969 and undated (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1979 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - 75th Anniversary Celebration of Rhodes Scholarship Program, 1978 (Box-folder 5/11)
- University of Montana, 1919-1979; Series V; 1.5 linear feet and partial oversize box
  This series documents Merrriam's long service to the university in Missoula as a professor and administrator. Much of the series consists of correspondence with university chancellors, administration, fellow professors and instructors, colleagues at other universities, students, and professional contract staff. Of particular note, the series includes an extensive sequence of correspondence and documents detailing the rationale employed to dismiss Merriam from his teaching position in 1939 as well as the campus and statewide response to the Board of Regents actions.
  This series includes a large file of correspondence regarding Merriam's retirement from the University of Montana in 1954. Most of the correspondents are former students expressing appreciation and admiration for his years of service and quality instruction. Notable correspondents include D'Arcy McNickle, Weldon Niva, Arthur Sanderson. S. Rae Logan, and Leslie Fiedler. The series also includes documents regarding Merriam's activities to create memorial funds to benefit university students and preserve the memory of his teaching colleagues. Lucia Mirrielees Memorial Fund Correspondence includes a memorial written about Edith Mirrielees, Lucia's sister. This document is retained in this folder as a reflection of Dr. Merriam's placement with such materials. Materials are arranged by subject, then chronologically.
  - Personnel and Administrative Documents, 1924-1971 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Official Correspondence, Chancellor Edward Elliot, 1919-1921 and undated (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Official Correspondence, University President Edward Sisson, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Official Correspondence, University President C.H. Clapp, 1921-1926 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Lectures at Summer Sessions, 1922-1924 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Concern for the University - correspondence and proposals, 1921-1950 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Official Correspondence, Chancellor Melvin Brannon, 1923-1932 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Correspondence, University President Candidates, 1935 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Official Correspondence, University President George Simmons, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1936 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1937 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1938 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Clippings, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1939-01 - 1939-08 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1939-09 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1939-10 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1939-11 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1939-12 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1940-01 - 1940-03 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Dismissal from University of Montana, Correspondence and Documents, 1940-04 - 1940-12 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Official Correspondence, University President George Simmons, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Course Materials, 1938-1953 and undated (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Correspondence, Search for university positions, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 7/9)